Consultant Profile Simplicity itself



Russell Miles

Respected IT thought-leader and technical architect

Brief

Russell has been working in the software development industry working since 1997 in a range of domains including Search through to Defence.

His roles in those domains have progressed through Developer, Senior Developer, Team Lead, and Senior Technologist responsible for multi-million pound research.

His highly practical leadership experience includes mentoring and encouraging teamwork, financial and resource budgeting, establishing and improving relationships with internal and external clients, managing the agile development process across multiple teams and product streams - all across a range of business critical projects.

He has also acted as business analyst and product manager, work that included as technical architecture within the design authority.

Russell has written three books for O'Reilly Media, there are other books in production.

Qualifications

BSc Computing (first class honours) - Greenwich University

MSc Software Engineering (distinction) - Oxford University

Role

Managing Director and Executive Principal Consultant

Experience summary

Commercial experience implementing, architecting, reviewing and trouble

shooting complex server side applications and platforms.

Certification Certified Scrum Master

Sun Certified Java Developer

Technical Review Russell has a broad spectrum of knowledge, particularly within open-source technologies. Below is a partial list of Russell's expertise.

> He also possesses exceptional technical writing skills and clearly articulates requirements both technically and to senior management and project sponsors.

> Russell has a high visibility 'brand'; frequently presenting within the UK and Europe at workshops and seminars.

Technical Overview

Java: Extensive Java experience with JDK 1.2-1.6, JEE development including JMS and

EJB

Complex high performance JSE multithreaded applications

Training: Considerable experience delivering training, authoring courseware and course

customisation.

Spring Data access, Aspect Orientated Programming, MVC, Web Services, Web Flow,

Framework: Integration, Spring for .Net

Persistence: JDBC, Hibernate, NHibernate, JPA, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Oracle

Development

Eclipse, Maven, ANT, Continuum, JIRA, Bamboo, Magicdraw UML, IDEA, Subversion and CVS, Git, JUnit, Visual Studio, Xcode, Oxygen XML

Testing: Test driven development Junit HttpUnit, Jmeter, Spock, Geb,

Hamcrest, Mockito

Operating systems:

tools:

Solaris, Linux (Ubuntu, Red hat/centos), Windows, Mac OS X

Servers: Tomcat, SpringSource DM Server (OSGi), WebLogic, ActiveMQ, WebSphere Domain: Utilities, Banking, Financial, Retail, Government, Virtualisation/

Cloud.

Contributions: XML, XPath, XSLT, Struts 1, Groovy, Grails, Ruby, Rails, Prolog

Employment History

Company	Simplicity Itself Ltd
Role	Founder and Principal Consultant.
Period	2012 -
Summary	Responsible for building an open source technical consultancy with a strong emphasis on open source; Russell attracts large corporate projects to the company through his established personal 'brand'.
	He personally works with a select number of long term clients in order to improve their software development productivity through process improvement, team coaching and technology recommendations, evaluations and development.
	Russell has established himself within the Cloud & Grid community leader, specifically with strategic partner; Skills Matter. In this role he engages with the cloud and grid community to provide popular courses, talks, blogging, conferences and courses.

Company	Open Credo Ltd - www.opencredo.com
Role	Managing Director and Principal Consultant.
Period	2009 - 2012
Summary	Responsible for building an open source technical consultancy with a strong emphasis on open source; Russell attracts large corporate projects to the company through his established personal 'brand'.
	He personally works with a select number of long term clients in order to improve their software development productivity through process improvement, team coaching and technology recommendations, evaluations and development.
	Russell has established himself within the Cloud & Grid community leader, specifically with strategic partner; Skills Matter. In this role he engages with the cloud and grid community to provide popular courses, talks, blogging, conferences and courses.

Company	SpringSource Ltd - www.springsource.com
Role	Senior Consultant.
Period	2008 - 2009
Summary	Russell was responsible for working with clients to get the most benefit out of applying best practices in productivity and the Spring framework. He was aligned with and contributed to the development of Spring for .NET, Spring Integration and Grails.
	He led and developed courseware for public and private training in Spring, AOP, Hibernate and Spring for .NET.
	Also was a widely sought public speaker; evangelising on Spring and general software development best practices at public speaking at various national and international conferences as well as for clients.
	He is author of "Spring in a Nutshell", currently in-progress.

Company	Contemporary Web Design Ltd
Role	Senior Consultant and Developer (contract)
Period	2007 – 2008
Summary	Responsible for the development and delivery of software on projects ranging in budgets from £1m to £15m; developing, managing and documenting solutions from concept, through architecture, implementation, and to delivery.
	Contributed to agile project planning and conducted day-to-day project activities; leading stand-up team meetings and delivering required documentation such as status reports and risk assessments. Steered and conducted development activities according to the changing requirements, liaising with the customer, high level client managers, product management and other contractors in order to deliver on time.
	Also conducted seminars and training on current and up-coming technologies and products; preparing and leading training courses in Mobile portal and storefront development. In addition, prepared and presented to Microsoft and Amazon in Seattle on AspectJ.
	Authored and published technical articles and books for O'Reilly Media;
	- Author of the "AspectJ Cookbook" - published in 2005 and translated into Chinese.
	- Co-author of "Learning UML 2.0" - published in 2006 and translated into French and Chinese.
	- Co-author of "Head First Software Development" - published 2008.
	- Range of other articles

Company	ASK.com
Role	JEE Architect and Developer (contract)
Period	2007
Summary	Designed, implemented and tested new front-end search features in order to deliver new product, Ask 3D.
	Development of Java and XML solutions for distributed high availability (5 9s), high traffic front end services. Development of design documentation. Use of best-practice design patterns. Maven, JUnit oriented code development. Proprietary Java and XML based framework business logic implementations, developing HTML and Javascript front-end functionality that integrated RESTful data services layer.
	Led inter-team communications on new technologies and new approaches that would significantly improve developer performance.

Company	Volantis Systems Ltd
Role	JEE Architect and Developer (contract)
Period	2006 - 2007
Summary	Architected, designed, implemented and tested high traffic, high availability mobile portals and storefronts. Development of Volantis Mobile Content Framework and Storefront solutions Du (Dubai), T-Mobile (Seattle), and MTN (South Africa).
	Developed Java and XML solutions for distributed high availability (5 9s), high traffic front end mobile services. Engaged and worked alongside the customer at all phases in the development process. Development of design documentation. Use of best-practice design patterns. Struts based business logic implementations, with JDBC, Entity Bean or Web Service based persistence layer.
	Also conducted training and evangelism on current and new product lines to high profile customers. Prepared and conducted training courses and product evangelism education to both internal and external customers including Du and T-Mobile.

Company	General Dynamics UK Ltd
Role	Senior Technologist, Lead Software Engineer and Team Leader
Period	1997 - 2006
Summary	Researched, Architected, designed, implemented and tested prototype tactical reconnaissance systems and associated technologies. Conducted leading edge research and authored several internal papers. Authored, resourced and executed technology roadmaps of values up to £3m. Sourced and managed a team of up to 10 senior developers using Agile methods. Conducted user-centric research capturing innovative requirements to improve workflows and capabilities. Developed UML models of high level system concerns as well as key functionality to guide the development process. Engaged and worked alongside the customer at all phases in the development process, including running workshops and running high level presentations.
	Led product development on a £2M project incorporating various software development streams. Researched and informed the marketing activities on projects together valuing at up to £1bn. Led and co-ordinated several teams in capturing, developing and supporting a large U.S. Reconnaissance product. Was responsible for reporting to upper management on all facets of the project. Visited and worked alongside the customer to ensure delivery of a product that matched their requirements. Provided technical architectural and design inputs to technical team leads. Regularly responsibly for technical input into marketing and work procurement activities such as authoring proposals, demonstrations and engaging the customer. Successfully worked as technical expert on the capture proposal and execution of a large, multi-national MoD procurement programme called MEC worth in excess of £5M to the company. Contributed to the capture and successful execution of the Bowman programme, worth a total of £1bn to the company.

Managed a team ranging from 3 to 15 people to successfully develop and deliver a range of products. Led and conducted an agile development process in order to deliver several internal and external products. Collaborated with other internal teams to deliver the overall project's goals. Reported to project management verbally and in written form, highlighting and dealing with risks that arose. Corporate representative to the NATO Standards Committee for the Intelligence Product Library. Responsible for developing and monitoring the development plans for the team, as well as conducting appraisals of individual performance and managing the team on a day-to-day basis.

Design authority, architected and developed several high-value and reusable products and closely worked on the creation of the development plans. Created a loosely coupled, language independent architecture for each of the products. Designed and developed key features of that architecture using Java, XML, Ada 95 and CORBA. Captured all designs decisions in a UML model using the IBM Rational product toolset. As design authority was responsible for communicating the architecture and design of the product to the rest of the team.

Also organised internal Tech Talks on current, new and upcoming technologies promoting investment in knowledge across the company. Created a series of technology talks that anyone in the company could attend that ran for a year. Personally created the content for and conducted 19 technology talks. Networked with existing product groups and individuals within the company to conduct talks.